What is a parent?
من هم الآباء؟
It's not an easy question.
هذا ليس بالسؤال السهل.
Today we have adoption,
اليوم نجد التبني،
stepfamilies,
العائلات غير البيولوجية،
surrogate mothers.
الأمهات البديلات.
Many parents face tough questions
يواجه العديد من الآباء والأمهات أسئلة صعبة
and tough decisions.
وقرارات صعبة.
Shall we tell our child about the sperm donation?
هل يجب إخبار أبنائنا عن التبرع بالحيوانات المنوية؟
If so, when?
إذا كان الأمر كذلك، فمتى ؟
What words to use?
و أي كلمات نستخدم؟
Sperm donors are often referred to as "biological fathers,"
غالبا ما يشار للمتبرعين بالحيوانات المنوية "بالآباء البيولوجيين"
but should we really be using the word "father?"
لكن هل يجب حقاً استخدام كلمة "آباء"؟
As a philosopher and social scientist,
كفيلسوفة وعالمة اجتماع،
I have been studying these questions about the concept of parenthood.
قمت بدراسة هذه الأسئلة حول مفهوم الأبوة،
But today, I will talk to you about what I learned
لكني اليوم ، سأتحدت لكم حول ماتعلمته
from talking to parents and children.
من خلال محادثاتي مع الآباء والأطفال.
I will show you that they know what matters most in a family,
وسوف أبين لكم أنهم يعلمون ما هو الشيء الأكثر أهمية في الأسرة؟
even though their family looks a little different.
على الرغم من كون أسرهم تبدو مختلفة قليلا.
I will show you their creative ways of dealing with tough questions.
سوف أظهر لك طرقهم الإبداعية في التعامل مع الأسئلة الصعبة.
But I will also show you the parents' uncertainties.
ولكن سوف أظهر لك أيضًا شكوك الوالدين .
We interviewed couples
أجرينا مقابلات مع الأزواج
who received fertility treatment at Ghent University Hospital,
الذين تلقوا علاج الخصوبة في مستشفى جامعة غنت،
using sperm from a donor.
باستخدام الحيوانات المنوية من متبرع.
In this treatment timeline,
خلال هذا العلاج،
you can see two points at which we conducted interviews.
يمكنك ملاحظة نقطتين محوريتين لهذه الحوارات
We included heterosexual couples,
أدرجنا الأزواج من جنسين مختلفين،
where the man for some reason did not have good-quality sperm,
حيث الرجل لسبب ما لم يكن لديه نوعية جيدة من الحيوانات المنوية،
and lesbian couples who obviously needed to find sperm elsewhere.
والأزواج المثليين الذين كانت لديهم حاجة للعثور على الحيوانات المنوية من مكان آخر.
We also included children.
وقد أدرجنا الأطفال أيضا
I wanted to know
أردت معرفة
how those children define concepts like parenthood and family.
كيف تعرّف هؤلاء الأطفال على مفاهيم مثل الأبوة والأسرة.
In fact, that is what I asked them,
في الواقع، كان هذا ما سألتهم عنه
only not in that way.
غير أنه كان بطريقةٍ أخرى.
I drew an apple tree instead.
فقد رسمت شجرة تفاح بدلاً من ذلك
This way, I could ask abstract, philosophical questions
بهذه الطريقة، صار بإمكاني أن أطرح أسئلة فلسفية مختصرة،
in a way that did not make them run off.
بطريقة لا تجعلهم يهربون من الأسئلة.
So as you can see,
إذن كما ترون،
the apple tree is empty.
شجرة التفاح فارغة.
And that illustrates my research approach.
و هذا يوضح نهج بحثي.
By designing techniques like this,
من خلال تصميم تقنيات مثل هذه،
I can bring as little meaning and content as possible to the interview,
فأتمكن من تحقيق أقل قدر من المعنى والمضمون للمقابلة،
because I want to hear that from them.
لأنني أريد سماع ذلك منهم .
I asked them:
سألتهم:
What would your family look like if it were an apple tree?
كيف كانت ستبدو عائلتك لو كانت شجرة تفاح؟
And they could take a paper apple for everyone who, in their view,
وكان بإمكانهم أخذ ورقة تفاح لكل شخص، من وجهة نظرهم،
was a member of the family,
كان عضوًا في الأسرة،
write a name on it and hang it wherever they wanted.
لكتابة اسم عليها وتعليقها أينما أرادوا.
And I would ask questions.
وسأقوم بطرح الأسئلة.
Most children started with a parent or a sibling.
معظم الأطفال بدأو بذكر الوالدين أو الاخوة.
One started with "Boxer,"
واحد بدأ بذكر "بوكسر"
the dead dog of his grandparents.
كلب جده الذي تُوُفّي.
At this point, none of the children started mentioning the donor.
حتى هذه اللحظة، لم يذكر أحد من الأطفال مانح الحيوان المنوي.
So, I asked them about their birth story.
لذلك، سألتهم عن قصة ولادتهم.
I said, "Before you were born,
قلت، "قبل ولادتك،
it was just your mom and dad,
كان هناك والدتك و ووالدك فقط،
or mom and mommy.
أو والدتك ووالدتك الثانية،
Can you tell me how you came into the family?"
هل يمكنك أن تخبرني كيف وصلت إلى هذه العائلة؟ "
And they explained.
وبدأوا بالشرح:
One said,
قال أحدهم،
"My parents did not have good seeds,
"والديّ لم يكن لديهم خصوبة جيدة،
but there are friendly men out there who have spare seeds.
لكن يوجد رجال طيبون لديهم خصوبة مناسبة.
They bring them to the hospital,
ذهبوا بهم إلى المستشفى،
and they put them in a big jar.
وضعوا حيواناتهم المنوية في وعاء كبير،
My mommy went there,
ذهبت أمي إلى هناك،
and she took two from the jar,
وأخذت اثنين من الجرة،
one for me and one for my sister.
واحدة لي ووحدة لأختي.
She put the seeds in her belly --
ووضعت الحيوانات المنوية في بطنها
somehow --
بطريقةٍ ما --
and her belly grew really big,
فنمى بطنها بطريقة هائلة،
and there I was."
وهكذا صرت أنا "
Hmm.
ممم
So only when they started mentioning the donor,
وبمجرد أن ذكروا المانح،
I asked questions about him, using their own words.
سألت مجموعة من الأسئلة عنه، باستخدام كلماتهم،
I said,
فقلت،
"If this would be an apple for the friendly man with the seeds,
اذا كانت هناك تفاحة للرجل الودود صاحب الحبوانات المنوية،
what would you do with it?"
ما الذي كنت ستفعله بها؟ "
And one boy was thinking out loud,
إذ بصبي كان يفكر بصوت عالي،
holding the apple.
ماسكاً التفاحة،
And he said,
وقال،
"I won't put this one up there with the others.
"أنا لن أضع هذه التفاحة هناك مع الآخرين.
He's not part of my family.
هو ليس جزءًا من عائلتي.
But I will not put him on the ground.
ولكني لن أضعه على الأرض.
That's too cold and too hard.
فهذا بارد جدا وصعب للغاية.
I think he should be in the trunk,
أعتقد أنه يجب أن يكون على الجذع،
because he made my family possible.
لأنه جعل عائلتي ممكنة.
If he would not have done this,
وإن لم يكن قد فعل هذا،
that would really be sad because my family would not be here,
فسيكون ذلك محزن حقًا لأن عائلتي لن تكون موجودة.
and I would not be here."
و لن أكون أنا هنا. "
So also, parents constructed family tales --
والآباء نسجوا حكايات العائلة أيضًا
tales to tell their children.
حكايات ليرووها لأبنائهم.
One couple explained their insemination
قام أحد الآباء بتفسير قصة تلقيحهم
by taking their children to a farm
عن طريق أخذ أطفالهم إلى مزرعة
to watch a vet inseminate cows.
لمشاهدة طبيب بيطري يقوم بتلقيح الأبقار.
And why not?
ولما لا؟
It's their way of explaining;
إنها طريقتهم في الشرح.
their do-it-yourself with family narratives.
قيامهم بصنع رواياتهم الخاصة بهم.
DIY.
اصنعها بنفسك.
And we had another couple who made books --
وقد كان لدينا زوجين آخرين ألّفا كتبا --
a book for each child.
كتاب لكل طفل.
They were really works of art
انهم فعلاً قطع فنية
containing their thoughts and feelings throughout the treatment.
تحتوي على أفكارهم ومشاعرهم طوال فترة العلاج.
They even had the hospital parking tickets in there.
حتى إنهم احتفظوا بتذاكر موقف السيارات هناك
So it is DIY:
لذلك فهي عملية " قم بها بنفسك " :
finding ways, words and images
إيجاد الطرق والكلمات والصور
to tell your family story to your child.
لسرد قصة عائلتك لطفلك.
And these stories were highly diverse,
وكانت هذه القصص متنوعة للغاية،
but they all had one thing in common:
لكنهم جميعًا يشتركون في شيء واحد:
it was a tale of longing for a child
وهو حكاية شوقهم لطفل
and a quest for that child.
والسعي لهذا الطفل.
It was about how special and how deeply loved their child was.
اشتركَت في مدى تميز هذا الطفل ومدى حبهم له
And research so far shows that these children are doing fine.
وتبين الابحاث أن هؤلاء الأطفال على ما يرام.
They do not have more problems than other kids.
ليس لديهم مشاكل أكثر من الأطفال الأخرين
Yet, these parents also wanted to justify their decisions
ومع ذلك، أراد هؤلاء الآباء والأمهات تبرير قراراتهم
through the tales they tell.
من خلال الحكايات التي رووها
They hoped that their children would understand their reasons
أملًا منهم أن يتفهم أطفالهم أسبابهم
for making the family in this way.
لتكوين أسرة بهذه الطريقة
Underlying was a fear that their children might disapprove
الخوف كان يكمن في أن أطفالهم قد لا يوافقون
and would reject the non-genetic parent.
أو يرفضون آباءهم غير البيولوجيين
And that fear is understandable,
وهذا الخوف أمر مفهوم،
because we live in a very heteronormative
لأننا نعيش في مجتمع يخضع لقوانين طبيعية
and geneticized society --
ومجتمع متوارث
a world that still believes
عالم لا يزال يعتقد
that true families consist of one mom, one dad
أن الأسر الحقيقية تتكون من أم واحدة وأب واحد
and their genetically related children.
وأبناء بيولوجيين
Well.
حسنًا.
I want to tell you about a teenage boy.
أريد أن أخبركم قصة عن صبي في سن المراهقة.
He was donor-conceived but not part of our study.
هو وُلد بالتخصيب، لكنه ليس جزءاً من دراستنا
One day, he had an argument with his father,
ذات يوم تشاجر مع والده
and he yelled,
وصاح،
"You're telling me what to do?
أتملي عليّ ما أفعل؟
You're not even my father!"
لست بأبي حتى!"
That was exactly what the parents in our study feared.
وكان هذا بالضبط ما يخشاه الآباء والأمهات في دراستنا.
Now, the boy soon felt sorry, and they made up.
الآن، هذا الصبي سرعان ما شعر بالأسف ،وتصالحا بعد ذلك
But it is the reaction of his father that is most interesting.
لكن الشيء الأكثر أهمية هنا هو رد فعل الأب.
He said,
قال،
"This outburst had nothing to do with the lack of a genetic link.
"هذا الغضب لم يكن له علاقة بانعدام الصلة الوراثية.
It was about puberty --
إنها فقط مرحلة المراهقة --
being difficult.
وكونها مرحلة صعبة.
It's what they do at that age.
هذا ما يفعلونه في هذه السن.
It will pass."
وسوف يمر ".
What this man shows us
ما يظهره هذا الرجل لنا
is that when something goes wrong,
أنه عندما تسير الأمور بشكل سيء
we should not immediately think
لا ينبغي لنا أن نفكر على الفور
it is because the family is a little different.
أن السبب يعود إلى كون الأسرة مختلفة قليلًا
These things happen in all families.
هذه الأمور تحدث في جميع العائلات.
And every now and then,
وبين الحين والآخر،
all parents may wonder:
قد يتساءل جميع الآباء والأمهات:
Am I a good enough parent?
هل أنا أب جيد؟
These parents, too.
هؤلاء الآباء جيدين أيضا.
They, above all, wanted to do what's best for their child.
هم، قبل كل شيء، يريدون فعل ما هو أفضل لأطفالهم.
But they also sometimes wondered:
لكنهم يتساءلون أحيانًا:
Am I a real parent?
هل أنا أب حقيقي؟
And their uncertainties were present long before they even were parents.
وقد كانت شكوكهم قائمة قبل كونهم آباءًا حتى
At the start of treatment,
في بداية العلاج،
when they first saw the counselor,
عندما رأوا أول مستشارطبي،
they paid close attention to the counselor,
أعطوا اهتمام دقيق إلى كلام المستشار الطبي
because they wanted to do it right.
لأنهم أرادوا فعل ذلك بالطريقة الصحيحة .
Even 10 years later,
و حتى بعد 10 اعوام،
they still remember the advice they were given.
سيتذكرون النصيحة التي قُدّمت لهم
So when they thought about the counselor
إذن عند تفكيرهم بالمستشار الطبي
and the advice they were given,
و النصيحة التي قًُدّمت لهم،
we discussed that.
ناقشنا ذلك.
And we saw one lesbian couple who said,
ورأينا زوجين مثليين قالا:
"When our son asks us,
"عندما سألَنا ابننا،
'Do I have a dad?'
'هل لدي أب؟ "
we will say 'No, you do not have a dad.'
سنقول "لا، ليس لديك أب".
But we will say nothing more, not unless he asks,
ولن نقول شيئا أكثر من ذلك،ما لم يسأل،
because he might not be ready for that.
لأنه قد لا يكون مستعدًا لذلك بعد.
The counselor said so."
هذا ما قاله المستشار الطبي."
Well.
حسناً.
I don't know; that's quite different
أنا حقاً لا أعرف ،إنه حقاً أمر مختلف
from how we respond to children's questions.
من كيفية الرد على بعض أسئلة أطفالنا.
Like, "Milk -- is that made in a factory?"
مثل."الحليب -- هل تم صنعه في المصنع؟"
We will say, "No, it comes from cows,"
سوف نقول : " لا ، الحليب يأتي من البقرة"
and we will talk about the farmer,
ثم سنتحدث حول المزارع،
and the way the milk ends up in the shop.
والطريقة التي يصل بها الحليب إلى المحلات.
We will not say,
لن نقول:
"No, milk is not made in a factory."
" لا ، الحليب لم يتم صنعه في المصنع."
So something strange happened here,
فهنا سيبدو بأنه شيء غريب وغير مألوف
and of course these children noticed that.
وبالتأكيد الأطفال لاحظوا ذلك.
One boy said,
واحد من الأولاد قال
"I asked my parents loads of questions,
" سألت والديّ الكثير من الأسئلة.
but they acted really weird.
لكنهم تصرفوا بغرابة شديدة.
So, you know, I have a friend at school, and she's made in the same way.
لذلك. لدي صديقة في المدرسة، ومرت بنفس التجربة.
When I have a question, I just go and ask her."
فعندما يكون لدي أسئلة, أذهب إليها على الفور."
Clever guy.
تصرف ذكي.
Problem solved.
تم حل المشكلة.
But his parents did not notice,
لكن والديه لم يلاحظا.
and it certainly was not what they had in mind,
وهو لم يكن ما اعتقداه،
nor what the counselor had in mind
ولا اعتقده المستشار الطبي
when they were saying how important it is to be an open-communication family.
عندما قالا بأنه أمر مهم أن يكونوا في عائلة متفاهمة ومتناقشة.
And that's the strange thing about advice.
وهذا هو الأمر الغريب حول النصيحة.
When we offer people pills, we gather evidence first.
عندما نعطي أدوية للناس، نبدأ أولاً بملاحظة الأعراض
We do tests,
نقوم باختبارات،
we do follow-up studies.
ثم نقوم بدراسات،
We want to know, and rightly so, what this pill is doing
نحن نريد أن نعرف حقاً ما الذي تفعله الأدوية
and how it affects people's lives.
وكيف تؤثر على حياة الناس
And advice?
ولكن ماذا عن النصيحة؟
It is not enough for advice,
هذا ليس كافياً للنصيحة،
or for professionals to give advice that is theoretically sound,
أوللمحترفين في إعطاء النصائح الصحيحة نظريا
or well-meant.
أو لحسن النية.
It should be advice that there is evidence for --
ينبغي أن تكون نصيحة ذات دليل
evidence that it actually improves patients' lives.
دليل يوضح بالضبط حياة المرضى.
So the philosopher in me would now like to offer you a paradox:
لذلك الفيلسوف الذي بداخلي يمكنه الآن أن يقدم تناقض
I advise you to stop following advice.
أنصحك فعلاً بالتوقف عن العمل بالنصائح.
But, yes.
لكن, حسناً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I will not end here with what went wrong;
أنا لن أنتهي هنا بما آل إلى شيء خاطيء
I would not be doing justice to the warmth we found in those families.
أنا لن أقوم بالحكم على الدفء الذي أحسسناه في هذه الأسر
Remember the books and the trip to the farmer?
هل تتذكرون الكتب ورحلة المزارع؟
When parents do things that work for them,
عندما يقوم الآباء بأشياء تؤدي الغرض لهم
they do brilliant things.
هم فعلاً يقومون بأشياء رائعة.
What I want you to remember as members of families,
ما أريدكم أن تتذكروه كأفراد في عائلاتكم
in no matter what form or shape,
لا يهم كيفية تكون العائلة،
is that what families need are warm relationships.
لكن أهم ما تحتاجه العائلة هو العلاقات الدافئة.
And we do not need to be professionals to create those.
ولا نحتاج أن نصبح خبراء في هذا الموضوع.
Most of us do just fine,
الكثير منا يفعله بشكل جيد،
although it may be hard work,
على الرغم من كونه شيء صعب.
and from time to time, we can do with some advice.
وبين الحين والآخر، يمكننا أن نفعله ببعض النصائح
In that case,
في هذه الحالة
bear in mind three things.
ضع في حسبانك ثلاثة أشياء مهمة.
Work with advice that works for your family.
استخدم النصيحة المناسبة لأسرتك
Remember -- you're the expert, because you live your family life.
تذكر -- أنت الأكثر خبرة لكنك أيضاً جزء من حياة أسرتك
And finally,
وأخيراً .
believe in your abilities and your creativity,
ثق في قدراتك وإبداعك.
because you can do it yourself.
لأنك تستطيع أن تفعلها بنفسك.
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيقات)